Finding Aid for Plaza Land Corporation records, 1955-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Plaza Land Corporation records 1955-1962
Plaza Land Corporation.
2012010 Bb 2
2.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from Susan Grace Glass and James Willard Grace in June 2011. (Donor no. 10594 ). Additional materials have been received.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Plaza Land Corporation was established in 1955 among a group of Detroit civic and business leaders for the purpose of acquiring property adjacent to the soon-to-be constructed "Convention Hall and Exhibits Building" (ultimately named for Detroit mayor at the time Albert E. Cobo) and acquiring the financing necessary for a new hotel to be built there. Originally the hotel was estimated to cost $24 million dollars. In 1956, the Plaza Land Corporation first turned to Conrad Hilton and the Hilton organization to own and operate the proposed hotel, which was originally to be named the Pontchartrain Hilton. In 1960, however, after four years of negotiation, the Hilton board of directors refused to ratify the deal. The Plaza Land Corporation sought out other investors and in 1962 successfully negotiated with the Downtown Investment Company, headed by Samuel and Aaron Gershenson, to take over construction and ownership of the proposed hotel. On July 24, 1965, the 264th anniversary of the founding of Detroit, the Hotel Pontchartrain was dedicated. The hotel was built on the site where Cadillac established the first fort in Detroit.
These records of the Plaza Land Corporation were accumulated and maintained by Edward R. Grace, secretary and member of the corporation's board of directors. The records, including minutes, memoranda, and correspondence, trace the development of what would become the Hotel Pontchartrain in Detroit. Within the records are files for the Corporation's various officers and directors, investors, and those otherwise closely associated with the project, including Detroit Mayor Albert E. Cobo, Conrad Hilton, Fred. C. Matthaei, H. Lynn Pierson, Douglas Roby, and Oscar Webber among others.
Subjects:
Hotel Pontchartrain (Detroit, Mich.); Plaza Land Corporation.; Cobo, Albert E. (Albert Eugene), 1893-1957.; Grace, Edward R.; Hilton, Conrad N. (Conrad Nicholson), 1887-1979.; Matthaei, Frederick C. (Frederick Carl), 1892-1973.; Pierson, H. Lynn.; Roby, Douglas F. (Douglas Fergusson), 1898-1992.; Webber, Oscar.; Hotels--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Commerce.
- Topical Files 1955-1962
  - Annual Reports (Box 1)
  - Arden, Armstrong Inquiry (Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation (Box 1)
  - Bassett, Arthur F. (Box 1)
  - Besimer, Fred (Box 1)
  - Blyth & Co., Inc. (Box 1)
  - Buhl, Charitable Trust, Finance Plan (Box 1)
  - Campbell, Harvey (Box 1)
  - Cobo, Albert E. (Box 1)
  - Comparison of Hotel, Operating Percentages, Horwath & Horwath, Harris Kerr (Box 1)
  - Convention and Exhibits Hall (Box 1)
  - Convention Information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, General (Box 1)
  - Corrigan Proposal (Box 1)
  - Crow, Allan (Box 1)
  - Dallas Opening (Box 1)
  - Detroit Hotels, Capacity & Operations (Box 1)
  - Detroit Tourist Statistics (Box 1)
  - Directors Meeting Letters (Box 1)
  - Dodds, John A.
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Proposal, Office Building (Box 1)
  - Ernst & Ernst (Box 1)
  - Finance Committee Meetings (Box 1)
  - Financial Statement, Plaza Land Corporation (Box 1)
  - Financing Report, Pontchartrain-Hilton Corporation (Box 1)
  - First of Michigan Corporation, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ford, Hilton (Foster Winter) (Box 1)
  - Ford Inquiry (Box 1)
  - Fruehauf, Roy (Box 1)
  - Garage (Box 1)
  - Glancy, A. R. (Box 1)
  - Grace, Pierson (Box 1)
  - Grace Proposals on Finance (Box 1)
  - Green, Mr. Leslie S. (Box 1)
  - Hall of Fame (Box 1)
  - Hall, Willis (Box 1)
  - Hilton Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hilton Hotel Operations, Los Angeles, Dallas, Washington, Detroit (Box 1)
  - Hilton Hotel Proposals, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hilton Hotel Reservation Data (Box 1)
  - Hockenbury Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Hockenbury Survey (Box 1)
  - Hotel Corporation of America (Box 1)
  - Hotels, Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
  - Industry Committees (Box 2)
  - Invitational Letter, Original (Box 2)
  - Kanzler, Ernest (Box 2)
  - Kapp, William E. (Box 2)
  - Klein, George (Box 2)
  - Lau, Norman (Box 2)
  - Leases (Box 2)
  - McHugh, Glenn (Box 2)
  - M (Box 2)
  - Markin, Ambassador Plan (Box 2)
  - Matthaei, Fred C. (Box 2)
  - Minutes of Directors Meetings (Box 2)
  - Notes from Stockholders Meetings, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Operation, Proposed Statement of (Box 2)
  - Other Hotel Operators (Box 2)
  - P (Box 2)
  - Personnel, Agency Services, Auto Account Administration (Box 2)
  - Pierson, H. Lynn (Box 2)
  - Plaza
    - Building (Box 2)
    - Finance (Box 2)
    - Finance Committee (Box 2)
    - Incorporators (Box 2)
    - Officers, Directors & Stockholders (Box 2)
    - Property Site (Box 2)
    - Site Data (Box 2)
  - Pontchartrain Plaza, Original Memos (Box 2)
  - Prudential Plan (Box 2)
  - Publicity, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Releases, Copies of (Box 2)
  - Roby, Douglas F. (Box 2)
  - Schine Hotels (Box 2)
  - Sheraton vs. Statler Operations, Detroit (Box 2)
  - Special Meetings (Box 2)
  - Stockholder Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Stockholders & Directors (Box 2)
  - Subscribers List (Box 2)
  - Webber, Finance Plan (Box 2)
  - Webber, Grace, Correspondence, copies (Box 2)
  - Webber, James B., Jr. (Box 2)
  - Webber, Newspaper Clippings (Box 2)
  - Webber, Oscar (Box 2)
  - Williford, Robert P. (Box 2)
- Supplementary material
  - Photographs: aerial photos of Detroit along the riverfront, also photos of renderings of the proposed convention center (Box 3)
  - Report: Pontchartrain Hilton; A New Hotel for Detroit circa 1956 (Box 3)
  - Magazine excerpt: Detroit as pictured in Fortune Magazine by The Detroit Bank 1954 (Box 3)
  - Fortune Magazine issue (January 1961) with article about Detroit (Box 3)
  - Pamphlet published under the auspice of the Michigan Society of Architects of a study of architects on the basic principles of city planning as applied to Detroit (Box 3)
  - Hotel Survey Report for Detroit, Michigan, Part II -- Community Interest 1956 (Box 3)
- Clippings and scrapbook
  - Scrapbook of clippings 1956-1959 (Box 3)
  - Clippings (Box 3)